what's up everybody phil bleckman with
barban.com and today we're going to talk
about some isometric movements that are
the best for core strength and full body
stability if you want to learn anything
about isometric movements in particular
just head over to google type in
isometric bar bend and all of that
information is going to come up there's
a lot to cover so let's get into it so
let's dive right in with the paused
squat whether performing the movement
with body weight or with a barbell the
squat is a stable movement pattern in
nearly every trainee's repertoire the
paused squat is more of a modification
than a new movement the lifter pauses at
the bottom of the lift removing momentum
from the bottom so that they have to
produce more force in order to stand
back up you can pause anywhere during
the squat although breaking at the
bottom is the most common you'll
accumulate more strength and muscle
building tension under the load as
you're holding it for an extended period
of time and pause squats are challenging
so you may not need as much weight on
the barbell as you would normally use
for a squat session moving on we're
going to talk about the paused bench
press much like the squat the paused
bench press takes advantage of removing
constant movement throughout the range
of motion to focus on control and
precision additionally you're going to
develop more pressing power as you need
to produce more force to get the barbell
from a dead stop over your chest when
using paused bench press reps the pause
bench press forces you to slow the
movement down and press with control
which means you'll need to dial in the
mechanics of your bench press in order
to lock it out safely the pause deadlift
is a popular deadlift variation among
powerlifters and strongmen to develop
more strength coming off of the floor
typically the lifter pulls the bar off
of the ground pauses at the shin and
then finishes the pull to the lockout
pausing at the shin creates a lot of
tension in the hamstrings and lower back
and fortifying these areas is a must for
effective and efficient deadlifts they
are after all critical players in this
compound movement benefits of paused
deadlifts include learning how to brace
better during the deadlift specifically
essential for bracing your spine when
pulling heavy weight and you'll build
stronger hamstrings glutes and quads
the front plank may seem like a vanilla
movement but it provides some of the
best value for no equipment out there
planking is likely one of the first
exercises to come to mind when
considering an isometric exercise and
for good reason a well-taught front
plank is the cornerstone for
conceptualizing and implementing
full-body isometric tension across a
multitude of exercises from the pause
squat to the overhead carry to the
deadlift to everything else benefits of
the front plank include better developed
anti-extension isometric core strength
learning the ability to generate full
body tension and it can be performed
anywhere with or without additional load
next up we have the ab wheel rollout the
ab wheel is a stable piece of equipment
in most commercial and home gyms alike
but often gets misused due to a lack of
understanding of its proper technique
the ab wheel is like a dynamic front
plank the front plank is an entirely
stationary isometric hold the ab wheel
takes the front plank and forces the
trainee to resist losing position while
the rest of the body moves throughout
the range of motion benefits of the ab
wheel roll out include integrating front
plank technique into a dynamic challenge
integrating hip and shoulder mobility
into the movement
and it requires no additional weight so
it can be performed more or less
anywhere those are just five isometric
exercises you can use to improve your
core strength and overall full body
mobility if you want to learn any other
isometric movements just head over to
google type in isometric bar bend and
all of that's going to come up we
specifically have an article that
touches on 11 isometric movements that
can benefit your training so next time
you head into the gym add some isometric
training into your routine to really
build out that core strength and full
body stability i'm phil blackman for
barbadon.com thanks for watching
[Music]
you